What do you see?
Apa yang kau lihat?
-Is a bird flying in the sky? -That's right.
- Apakah burung terbang di langit? - Benar.
It flew over to the other side of the sun. Where did it go?
Burungnya terbang ke sisi lain matahari. Ke mana perginya?
It must've gone to the other world.
Pasti ke dunia lain.
Can't you see? Take a good look.
Kau tak lihat? Perhatikan baik-baik.
I can't see it.
Aku tak bisa melihatnya.
-Shall I help you see it? -Yes.
- Mau kubantu? - Ya.
All right.
Baiklah.
Have a good look.
Perhatikan baik-baik.
The world we're living in consists of the part where we reside
Dunia tempat kita hidup terdiri dari bagian tempat kita tinggal
and the other part over there.
dan bagian lain di sana.
This is where we live,
Ini tempat tinggal kita,
and the gods live in the other part of the world.
dan para dewa tinggal di bagian lain.
"The gods"?
"Para dewa?"
The world of the gods consists of the Land of Water,
Dunia para dewa terdiri dari Negeri Air,
the Land of the Sky, and the Land of Earth.
Negeri Langit, dan Negeri Tanah.
They send deities to our world
Dewa dikirim ke dunia kita
to look after and protect nature in the human realm.
untuk menjaga dan melindungi alam di dunia manusia.
Do they look after humans too?
Apa mereka menjaga manusia juga?
Human beings will figure things out on their own.
Manusia bisa mencari jawaban sendiri.
The Kings of the Land of Water, Land of the Sky, and Land of Earth
Raja Negeri Air, Raja Negeri Langit, dan Raja Negeri Tanah
were born with the fate of becoming rulers.
terlahir dengan takdir sebagai penguasa.
The King of the Land of Water, from where all things originate,
Raja Negeri Air, tempat semua hal berasal,
is given absolute authority which makes him the King of the Kings.
diberikan otoritas mutlak yang menjadikannya Raja Diraja.
In order to ascend to the throne, they must make their royal seals
Untuk naik takhta, mereka harus membuat segel kerajaan
with the sacred stone that has a holy message engraved on it,
menggunakan batu keramat yang terukir ramalan,
but that stone is kept by the gods who reside in the human world.
tapi batu itu disimpan oleh para dewa yang tinggal di dunia manusia.
That means they have to come here and get the stone
Maka mereka harus ke sini dan mengambilnya
if they wish to become the ruler of the divine world.
jika ingin jadi penguasa kayangan.
That's correct.
Itu benar.
But what if those deities refuse to give it to them?
Tapi bagaimana jika para dewa itu tak mau memberikannya ke mereka?
Only humans do things like that.
Hanya manusia yang melakukan hal macam itu.
But there's something I don't understand.
Tapi ada sesuatu yang tak kumengerti.
Why is the sacred stone kept in the human world?
Kenapa batu keramat disimpan di dunia manusia?
UNDYING CONNECTION BETWEEN PARENTS AND CHILDREN
HUBUNGAN ABADI ANTARA ORANG TUA DAN ANAK
YEAR 2018
TAHUN 2018
ONE YEAR AGO
1 TAHUN YANG LALU
High Priest.
Pendeta Agung.
It's about time the red tide rushed in.
Sudah saatnya gelombang merah datang.
The divine realm will welcome a new emperor after 3,000 years.
Kayangan akan menyambut seorang kaisar baru setelah 3.000 tahun.
I am beyond honored to be given this opportunity.
Saya merasa amat terhormat atas kesempatan ini.
Thank you for your boundless generosity, Lord Habaek.
Terima kasih atas kebaikan Anda yang tak terbatas, Tuan Habaek.
Painting your noble face
Melukis wajah Anda yang agung
is making me understand why the universe has chosen you
membuat saya paham kenapa alam semesta memilih Anda
to be our next king.
menjadi raja kami berikutnya.
Now, please open your eyes...
Sekarang, mohon buka mata Anda…
Please allow me to complete the most important part of this...
Tolong izinkan saya menyelesaikan bagian terpenting ini…
My lord, the High Priest asked me to pass along this message to you.
Tuan, Pendeta Agung meminta saya menyampaikan pesan ini kepada Anda.
Tell him to stop sending me these messages.
Suruh dia berhenti mengirim pesan kepadaku.
Does he have that much to say? He does this every day.
Sebanyak itukah yang harus dia sampaikan? Setiap hari begini.
He said that the waters have reddened...
Katanya lautan sudah berubah merah
and that you should get ready.
dan Anda harus bersiap.
Is His Majesty aware of it too?
Yang Mulia tahu soal ini?
He is delighted.
Beliau gembira.
He has been waiting for the red tide for a long time.
Beliau sudah menunggu gelombang merah sejak lama.
He has been on the throne for eons.
Beliau bertakhta selama ribuan tahun.
He must be exhausted.
Beliau pasti lelah.
This shows the locations of the three deities with the sacred stone.
Ini menunjukkan lokasi dari tiga dewa dengan batu keramat.
This will lead you to them.
Ini akan menuntunmu pada mereka.
My lord.
Tuan.
Mura is there from the Land of Water. The Land of Earth must've sent Judong.
Mura dari Negeri Air ada di sana. Negeri Tanah pasti mengirim Judong.
-What about the Land of the Sky? -It's Biryeom.
- Bagaimana dengan Negeri Langit? - Biryeom.
What...
Apa…
-Biryeom? -The enthronement must take place
- Biryeom? - Penobatan harus dilakukan
after the seventh red tide,
setelah gelombang merah ke-7,
so you just have to come back with the sacred stone before that.
jadi kau harus kembali dengan batu keramat sebelum itu terjadi.
-I'll come back right away. -Why?
- Aku akan segera kembali. - Kenapa?
The world of mankind is actually a pretty fun place.
Dunia manusia sebenarnya tempat yang menyenangkan.
We have plenty of time before the last tide,
Kita punya banyak waktu sebelum gelombang terakhir,
-so you should have some fun. -I'm not interested.
- jadi  bersenang-senanglah. - Aku tak tertarik.
By the way, why do we still have to follow such meaningless customs?
Kenapa kita masih harus mengikuti adat tak bermakna seperti ini?
Nothing in this world is meaningless.
Tak ada satu pun di dunia ini yang tak bermakna.
Anyway,
Omong-omong,
I'll get rid of such meaningless customs as soon as I ascend to the throne.
aku akan menyingkirkan adat tak bermakna ini begitu aku naik takhta.
Sure.
Tentu.
You can do as you please once you are on the throne.
Kau bisa berbuat sesukamu saat bertakhta.
It sounds like you're doubting whether I can really do it.
Sepertinya
Of course not.
Tentu tidak.
You were born to be a king, my lord.
Kau terlahir untuk menjadi raja, Tuanku.
The throne will become yours, even if you don't do anything.
Takhta akan menjadi milikmu bahkan jika kau tak melakukan apa pun.
No one can refute that unless they're crazy.
Tak ada yang akan membantah itu kecuali orang gila.
Becoming a king in the divine realm has nothing to do with humans,
Menjadi raja di kayangan tak berkaitan dengan manusia,
so why is the sacred stone kept there?
kenapa batu keramat ada di sana?
What a hassle.
Merepotkan.
Well...
Jadi...
you have a question,
Karena kau punya pertanyaan,
so you should stay there for a while and find the answer.
tinggallah sementara di sana dan temukan jawabannya.
It wasn't a question.
Itu bukan pertanyaan.
Oh, right. You've heard about the divine servants, right?
Kau pernah dengar soal para pelayan surgawi, 'kan?
Humans who made a pledge to serve us generation after generation.
Manusia dan keturunanya yang bersumpah melayani kita.
If you run into problems, find descendants of that family.
Jika kau menghadapi masalah, cari keturunan dari keluarga itu.
Showing this to them
Menunjukkan ini
will naturally awaken them.
pada mereka akan membangunkan mereka.
Then they'll serve you as their god.
Mereka akan melayanimu.
I don't need it. I won't look for them.
Aku tak butuh itu. Aku tak akan mencari mereka.
It's a girl.
Dia seorang gadis.
Would you like to see her face?
Kau mau melihat wajahnya?
She's not bad.
Dia lumayan cantik.
No need.
Tak perlu.
Namsuri will be escorting you.
Namsuri akan mengawalmu.
Keep the sacred pendant on you at all times, even if it's inconvenient.
Mohon selalu kenakan kalung keramat meskipun tidak nyaman.
Don't leave it with your clothes.
Jangan ditinggal bersama pakaianmu.
The Land of the Sky has gone crazy.
Negeri Langit sudah gila.
They put Biryeom in charge of looking after the sky.
Mereka membuat Biryeom bertugas menjaga langit.
That punk is incapable of doing any work.
Bajingan itu tidak becus.
Why do you hate Biryeom so much?
Kenapa kau begitu membencinya?
You two used to be close friends.
Kalian dulu bersahabat.
He has no class.
Dia tak berkelas.
Also,
Dan juga,
he's not reliable.
dia tak bisa diandalkan.
You should learn about the human world before you go.
Sebelum pergi, pelajarilah dunia manusia.
That's why I'm taking you with me.
Itu sebabnya aku mau mengajakmu.
I heard you've been to the world of mankind.
Kudengar kau pernah ke dunia manusia.
Sure. I do know a lot about it.
Tentu. Aku tahu banyak hal soal manusia.
The moment you pass the Divine Gate, you'll feel a sting.
Saat kita melewati Gerbang Surgawi, kita akan merasakan sengatan.
But it's not that bad.
Tapi tak sakit.
Get me the best kinds of clothes that humans wear.
Berikan aku jenis pakaian terbaik yang dipakai manusia.
And don't forget a gift for Mura.
Dan jangan lupa hadiah untuk Mura.
Have you seen the servant yet?
Kau sudah melihat pelayannya?
I heard it's a woman.
Dia wanita.
Is she pretty?
Apa dia cantik?
Oh, yes. Sure.
Ya. Tentu.
I received a revelation from the alien gods of the planet Intro Q 2544.
Aku menerima ramalan dari dewa alien planet Intro Q 2544.
My supervisor is TF 1004. He seemed to be in a huge rush.
Supervisorku adalah TF 1004.
I see. What else?
Oh, begitu. Apa lagi?
Here on Earth, there are partners who carry out such divine messages like I do.
Di bumi ini, ada rekan lain yang mengantarkan pesan surgawi seperti aku.
The organization is spread throughout the world.
Organisasinya tersebar di seluruh dunia.
But the strange thing is,
Tapi anehnya,
why did they send this divine message to me
kenapa mereka mengirim pesan surgawi ini kepadaku
instead of the US partner? That's my question.
dan bukan rekan di AS? Itu pertanyaanku.
Right. I wonder why.
Benar. Entah kenapa.
"Inform Obama. World peace is under threat."
"Beri tahu Obama. Perdamaian dunia terancam."
That's what it means.
Itu artinya.
Are you...
Apakah kau…
What should I do? I don't know the address.
Aku harus bagaimana? Aku tak tahu alamatnya.
Do you know that he's out of the White Roof House?
Apa kau tahu dia tak lagi di Gedung Putih?
So, even you don't believe me.
Bahkan kau pun tak percaya aku.
Don't say that. You're my patient, so--
Jangan begitu. Kau pasienku...
What? Did you just call me a patient?
Apa? Kau memanggilku pasien?
Again?
Lagi?
-Hey! -I didn't mean...
- Hei! - Aku tak bermaksud...
-As a patient-- -I'm not a patient!
- Sebagai pasien... - Aku bukan pasien!
Right, Mr. Ma Bong-yeol.
Benar, Tn. Ma Bong-yeol.
I'll try my best to get Obama's address--
Aku akan mencari alamat Obama...
-Gosh! -Don't lie to my face!
- Astaga! - Jangan bohong!
You don't even believe me!
Kau bahkan tak percaya aku.
Doctor. Doctor, please.
Dokter. Dokter, tolonglah.
No one believes me. World peace is--
Tak ada yang percaya kepadaku. Perdamaian dunia...
Let go, please.
Lepaskan!
It's under threat.
Perdamaian terancam!
-Sir. Mr. Ma. -World peace
- Tn. Ma. - Perdamaian dunia
-is under threat. -Please let go of her.
- sedang terancam. - Tolong lepaskan dia.
It's true that world peace is under threat.
Benar bahwa perdamaian dunia terancam.
You...
Kau...
Can you speak our language?
Kau mengerti bahasa kami?
Of course. It's nice to meet you.
Tentu saja. Senang bertemu denganmu.
I'm glad to meet you.
Senang bertemu denganmu.
Let's get out of here.
Ayo pergi dari sini.
This way. Go on.
Lewat sini. Ayo.
Let's go.
Ayo.
-How could you communicate with him? -I observed him.
- Kau bisa berkomunikasi dengannya? - Aku mengamatinya.
It sounds like total bullshit, but it's systematic like the Korean alphabet.
Terdengar seperti omong kosong, tapi sistematis seperti alfabet Korea.
He's very smart, you know.
Dia sangat pintar.
You're much better than me.
Kau lebih baik dariku.
His family wanted to keep him in the hospital, right?
Keluarganya ingin menahannya di RS, 'kan?
I can't handle him. Schedule an appointment.
Aku tak sanggup menanganinya. Buatkan janji.
-Come on. Don't give up so easily. -You think I'm giving up easily?
Ayolah. Jangan cepat menyerah.
Hey, I've been treating him for a year.
Hei, aku merawatnya selama setahun.
Admitting failure is never easy.
Mengakui kegagalan tidak mudah.
Should I keep him for the sake of my pride?
Harus kurawat dia demi harga diri?
-I'm sick of it. -I get it.
- Aku muak. - Aku mengerti.
Half of these are payment reminders.
Setengahnya peringatan pembayaran.
DA DA FINANCIAL
DA DA FINANCIAL
The bank called to say they can't give you
Bank menelepon, mereka tak bisa
-another extension. -What?
- berikan perpanjangan lain. - Apa?
Why not?
Kenapa tidak?
The clinic is not doing well, and you don't pay the interest on time.
Kliniknya tidak ramai, dan kau tak membayar bunga tepat waktu.
Then what? Do they want this clinic to be shut down?
Lalu apa? Mereka mau klinik ini ditutup?
I guess so.
Kurasa begitu.
Get out.
Keluar.
-Give me your gown. I'll wash it for you. -Forget it.
- Berikan jasmu. Akan kucuci. - Lupakan.
Do you want to grab a drink with me?
Kau mau minum denganku?
Why would I grab a drink with you?
Kenapa aku mau minum denganmu?
I forgot to give you this. It's for your land in Gangwon Province.
Aku lupa memberimu ini. Ini untuk tanahmu di Provinsi Gangwon.
PROPERTY TAX
PAJAK PROPERTI
It still hasn't sold?
Itu masih belum terjual?
Who'd buy such a useless piece of land filled with stones?
Siapa yang mau beli tanah tak berguna penuh batu?
I really didn't need to inherit this.
Aku seharusnya tak mewarisi ini.
We're really behind on our rent as well.
Kita juga telat bayar sewa.
And you've already spent half of the rent deposit.
Dan separuh deposit sewa sudah kau habiskan.
By the way, why do you still work for me?
Omong-omong, kenapa kau masih bekerja untukku?
Quit now.
Berhentilah.
I want to repay the kindness I received.
Aku ingin membalas kebaikan yang kuterima.
-Your father-- -Shut it.
- Ayahmu... - Diam.
I don't want to hear it.
Aku tak mau dengar itu.
By the way,
Omong-omong,
do you still dream of leaving this country for good?
apa kau masih bermimpi meninggalkan negara ini?
Yes. As soon as I pay off all my debt,
Ya. Begitu aku melunasi semua utangku,
I'll pack up and move to Vanuatu.
aku akan berkemas dan pindah ke Vanuatu.
Just find a guy who will clear your debt for you
Cari pria yang bisa melunasi utangmu
and stay here.
dan tetaplah tinggal di sini.
No way. I don't like Korea.
Tak mungkin. Aku tak suka Korea.
Or maybe men don't like you.
Atau mungkin pria tak menyukaimu.
Hey, I even got a diamond ring from a wealthy man.
Hei, aku bahkan mendapat cincin berlian dari pria kaya.
Found it.
Ketemu.
I actually got this ring from a man. Why wouldn't he believe me?
Aku dapat cincin ini dari seorang pria. Kenapa dia tak percaya padaku?
I found you because you were obviously meant to be mine.
Aku menemukanmu karena kau jelas ditakdirkan jadi milikku.
I can't believe his name is Ahn Bin.
Aku tak percaya namanya Ahn Bin.
It sounds so childish.
Kedengarannya kekanak-kanakan.
Take care of all the bills and my interest payments.
Semua tagihan dan pembayaran bungaku lunas.
Vanuatu, my love.
Vanuatu, Cintaku.
Yes.
Ya.
That's how life is supposed to be.
Begitulah seharusnya hidup.
I can't see a single star in this polluted country.
Aku tak bisa melihat satu pun bintang di negara berpolusi ini.
I want money! Please help me roll in money.
Aku mau uang! Beri aku uang yang banyak.
Hey, woman.
Hei, wanita.
Woman.
Wanita.
I shall give you the honor of lending me this.
Aku memberimu kehormatan meminjamkan ini padaku.
Hey, woman.
Hei, wanita.
Wake up.
Bangun.
You shouldn't sleep here.
Jangan tidur di sini.
This woman is such a nuisance.
Wanita ini merepotkan sekali.
What?
Apa?
What's going on?
Apa yang terjadi?
Hey, you thief!
Pencuri sialan!
How dare you call me a thief, you rude woman!
Beraninya kau menyebutku pencuri, dasar wanita kasar.
I shall punish you later.
Akan kuhukum kau nanti.
What has happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
Namsuri. What happened to him?
Namsuri. Apa yang terjadi dengannya?
My lord! You made it down here safe and sound.
Tuan! Kau tiba dengan selamat.
-What happened? -I don't know.
- Apa yang terjadi? - Entahlah.
I landed over there.
Aku mendarat di sana.
What happened to you?
Apa yang terjadi padamu?
That's what I wanted to ask you. Why are you wearing my clothes?
Itu yang ingin kutanyakan. Kenapa memakai pakaianku?
Pardon?
Maaf?
How did this happen?
Bagaimana ini bisa terjadi?
Let's switch.
Ayo bertukar.
This is strange.
Ini aneh.
The Divine Gate looks different from what I saw 55 years ago.
Gerbang Surgawi terlihat berbeda dari yang kulihat 55 tahun lalu.
Look closely.
Perhatikan baik-baik.
Here, a lot can change, even in just ten years.
Di sini, banyak yang bisa berubah bahkan dalam sepuluh tahun.
The land that is used as the Divine Gate never changes.
Tanah yang digunakan sebagai Gerbang Surgawi tak pernah berubah.
Then something must have gone wrong on our way here.
Maka pasti ada yang salah dalam perjalanan ke sini.
-Where's the map? -Pardon? Don't you have it?
- Di mana petanya? - Apa? Kau tak memegangnya?
Gosh!
Astaga.
Use your abilities to find it.
Cari itu dengan kekuatanmu.
Did you find it, my lord?
Ketemu, Tuan?
What's wrong?
Ada apa?
It's strange.
Aneh.
I feel as if...
Aku merasa
something...
seolah sesuatu...
has left my body.
telah meninggalkan tubuhku.
"Something"?
"Sesuatu"?
How could this happen?
Bagaimana ini bisa terjadi?
You lost your abilities?
Kekuatanmu hilang?
Let's go back to the Land of Water for now.
Mari kembali ke Negeri Air.
-Take me to the Divine Gate. -We can't go back now.
- Bawa aku ke Gerbang Surgawi. - Tak bisa.
All gods must fulfill their duties in order to return.
Semua dewa harus memenuhi tugas mereka agar bisa kembali.
I told you to study.
Aku menyuruhmu belajar.
First, let's find the descendant of the servant.
Pertama, mari kita cari keturunan pelayan.
We need her help now.
Kita butuh bantuannya.
You don't have it?
Hilang?
What are we going to do now?
Bagaimana ini?
-Let me get a change of clothes first. -I'm okay.
- Izinkan aku ganti pakaian dahulu. - Aku tak perlu.
I'm not okay.
Aku perlu.
Please stay put.
Tolong tunggu di sini.
Don't be so confident and arrogant all the time.
Jangan terlalu percaya diri dan arogan.
And don't order anyone around, okay?
Dan jangan memerintah siapa pun, ya?
All right.
Baiklah.
Gosh, this is crazy.
Astaga, ini gila.
No.
Tidak.
That can't be.
Ini mustahil.
It's probably just a temporary phenomenon.
Mungkin ini hanya sementara.
I couldn't use my power during my first visit
Aku tak bisa memakai kekuatanku
to the Land of the Sky.
saat kunjungan pertamaku ke Negeri Langit.
So where are you now?
Di mana kau sekarang?
How many times do I have to tell you? He stole my diamond ring.
Berapa kali aku harus memberitahumu? Dia mencuri cincin berlianku.
I'm not drunk, okay?
Aku tidak mabuk, oke?
I am Habaek.
Aku Habaek.
Why did I come to the park?
Kenapa aku datang ke taman?
I told you that I'm here to find my diamond ring.
Sudah kubilang, aku di sini untuk menemukan cincin berlianku.
What? I'm delusional?
Apa? Aku berdelusi?
Hey.
Hei.
Where are you?
Di mana kau?
I am...
Aku...
Habaek.
Habaek.
Just answer my question.
Jawab saja pertanyaanku.
I am...
Aku...
Habaek.
Habaek.
Where are you, you idiot?
Di mana kau? Dasar bodoh.
I am Habaek.
Aku Habaek.
-Where? -I am Habaek!
- Di mana? - Aku Habaek!
Jeez, that totally scared me.
Astaga, itu menakutkan.
See? I am Habaek.
Lihat? Aku Habaek.
It's working fine.
Berfungsi dengan baik.
There's nothing wrong with it.
Tak ada masalah.
Turn it off for now.
Matikan sekarang.
Let's test it a few more times.
Ayo ulangi beberapa kali lagi.
It's that woman.
Wanita itu lagi.
What is he doing? Is he walking toward me?
Apa yang dia lakukan? Dia berjalan ke arahku?
Do I know that guy?
Apa aku kenal pria itu?
No, I don't know him.
Tidak, aku tak mengenalnya.
Hey, woman.
Hei, wanita.
You're mistaken. I'm only borrowing it.
Kau salah paham. Aku hanya meminjamnya.
Sorry?
Maaf?
-Me? -If you tell me your name
- Aku? - Jika kau beri tahu namamu
and where you live, I'll have Namsuri pay you back.
dan tempat tinggalmu, Namsuri akan membayarmu kembali.
What do you need?
Apa yang kau butuhkan?
Seriously, even such a handsome guy can be mentally ill.
Astaga, pria tampan sekalipun bisa sakit jiwa.
You should go home. Your family must be worried.
Kau harus pulang. Keluargamu pasti cemas.
-Don't hesitate to tell me. -It's fine.
- Jangan ragu untuk memberi tahu. - Tak apa-apa.
How insolent.
Lancang sekali!
I asked you a question. I didn't say you could go.
Aku bertanya, aku tak bilang kau boleh pergi.
For goodness' sake.
Demi Tuhan.
I...
Aku...
Could he be delusional?
Mungkin dia delusi?
What is it that you need?
Apa yang kau butuhkan?
Money?
Uang?
"Money"?
"Uang"?
What is that?
Apa itu?
Never mind. You should hurry home.
Lupakan. Kau harus cepat pulang.
Bye now.
Selamat tinggal.
-Let go! -Your name and where you live.
- Lepaskan! - Nama dan tempat tinggalmu.
Let go of my hand, or I'll call the police.
Lepaskan tanganku atau kutelepon polisi.
-I said, let go! -Doctor!
- Kubilang, lepas! - Dokter!
What are you doing? Let go!
Apa yang kau lakukan? Lepaskan!
Let go of her. Don't do this.
Lepaskan dia. Jangan begitu.
Such insolence. How dare you!
Lancang sekali. Beraninya kau.
What happened to your forehead?
Kenapa dahimu?
-Did he hit you? -No, it's fine. Let's go.
- Dia memukulmu? - Tidak apa-apa. Ayo.
I'm the God of Water,
Aku Dewa Air,
the next king of the Land of Water and the next emperor of the gods,
calon Raja Negeri Air, dan calon kaisar para dewa,
Habaek.
Habaek.
I knew it.
Sudah kuduga.
He's absorbed by grandiose delusions.
Dia menderita waham kebesaran.
Here.
Ini.
Come visit us. It's not far from here.
Mampirlah. Kliniknya dekat.
Our doctor is very good.
Dokter kami sangat bagus.
I hope to see you soon.
Semoga kita bertemu lagi.
You know you're cut out to be a psychiatrist, right?
Kau tahu kau cocok jadi psikiater, bukan?
People who need you come to you day and night.
Orang yang membutuhkanmu datang siang dan malam.
Be quiet.
Diam.
I'm sure you'll only find people like him, even in Vanuatu.
Aku yakin kau akan menemukan orang seperti dia bahkan di Vanuatu.
Wouldn't it be better to stay here?
Bukankah lebih baik tetap di sini?
I think Korea is still better.
Kurasa Korea masih lebih baik.
Where's the nearest police station?
Di mana kantor polisi terdekat?
Why do you ask?
Memang kenapa?
-Are you going to report it? -Yes.
- Kau mau melapor? - Ya.
Calm down. He's not all there.
Tenanglah. Dia tak waras.
I'm going to file a report about my diamond ring.
Aku mau melapor soal cincin berlianku.
Are you still drunk?
Kau masih mabuk?
They'll look into it and get in touch with us.
Mereka akan selidiki dan hubungi kita.
Are you mad at me?
Apa kau marah padaku?
I don't think you believe me.
Kurasa kau tak percaya aku.
Let's say I believe you about the diamond ring buried under a tree.
Anggap aku percaya tentang cincin berlian yang terkubur di bawah pohon.
But you also went on about the star frantically moving from left to right.
Masalahnya, kau juga bicara soal bintang yang bergerak dari kiri ke kanan.
And the thief who fell from the sky didn't take your wallet.
Dan pencuri yang jatuh dari langit tak menyentuh dompetmu.
Why? So that you'd have money to get around?
Kenapa? Agar kau dapat uang?
It really happened!
Itu sungguh terjadi!
Shall I get you a glass of cold water or what?
Mau kuambilkan segelas air dingin?
Right, she doesn't like cold water. How about some warm water?
Oh, dia tak suka air dingin.
What took you so long?
Kenapa lama sekali?
I tried to get some information about this world from humans
Aku mencari informasi soal dunia ini dari manusia
and find a place for you to stay tonight.
dan tempat untuk menginap malam ini.
Let's go, my lord. I've found a good place.
Mari, Tuan. Aku menemukan tempat yang bagus.
-It's close to water too. -There's no need.
- Dekat perairan juga. - Tak perlu.
-I got my abilities back. -Seriously?
- Kemampuanku kembali. - Sungguh?
The water you see behind us
Air yang kau lihat
splashed up as per my command.
di belakang langsung menyembur begitu kuperintah.
I knew it.
Sudah kuduga.
Then please go ahead and turn it into gold.
Silakan mengubahnya menjadi emas.
You'll be comfortable here since it's very close to water.
Kau akan merasa nyaman di sini karena dekat dengan air.
This is it.
Ini dia.
I took a while because I had to inflate this.
Aku lama karena harus meniup ini.
A man gave it to me earlier, saying I should visit.
Seorang pria memberinya padaku, katanya aku harus mampir.
You spoke with a human?
Tuan bicara dengan manusia?
I told you not to say a word.
Seharusnya jangan bicara.
"Blessed Mental Health,
"Klinik Jiwa Blessed,
Nurse Yu Sang-yu"?
Perawat Yu Sang-yu"?
What?
Apa?
Oh, I was just reading what's written here.
Aku membaca tulisan di sini.
You can't read the human alphabet, right?
Kau tak bisa baca huruf manusia, 'kan?
Sleep well, my lord.
Tidurlah yang nyenyak, Tuan.
I'll stand guard here all night.
Aku akan berjaga sepanjang malam.
I'll try to find the map as soon as the sun comes up.
Akan kucari petanya segera setelah fajar tiba.
In the human world, money can solve most problems.
Di dunia manusia, uang bisa memecahkan banyak masalah.
What is it that you need?
Apa yang kau butuhkan?
Money?
Uang?
You're not pronouncing that word correctly.
Kau tak mengucapkan kata itu dengan benar.
It's "money," you dummy.
Yang benar "uang", bodoh.
Happy Bank also called for you.
Bank Happy juga meneleponmu.
-Did you take another loan out? -It wasn't me.
- Kau ambil pinjaman lagi? - Bukan aku.
Right.
Benar.
Selling the diamond ring won't solve my problems.
Menjual cincin berlian tak akan memecahkan masalahku.
"Money"?
"Uang"?
What is that?
Apa itu?
Right, that probably allows him to be carefree.
Benar, itu mungkin membuatnya masa bodoh.
That's how life should be.
Begitulah seharusnya hidup.
Let's talk while looking around the resort.
Mari bicara sambil keliling resor.
Is the food and beverage team going first?
Tim makanan dan minuman yang pertama?
We have a banquet with 200 Chinese guests scheduled for today.
Ada pesta yang dihadiri 200 tamu Tiongkok hari ini.
The owner of a Chinese harbor construction company will be there.
Pemilik perusahaan konstruksi pelabuhan Tiongkok akan hadir.
You should attend it so that--
Kau harus hadir agar...
I won't need to attend it as he's not a national VIP.
Aku tak perlu hadir karena dia bukan VIP nasional.
-Anything from the planning team? -Yes, sir.
- Info dari tim perencanaan? - Ya, Pak.
This is the British company's revised construction proposal.
Ini revisi proposal konstruksi perusahaan Inggris.
The location is the same. It's the site you checked the other day.
Lokasinya sama. Ini lokasi yang diperiksa kemarin.
It's not bad. As long as everything is okay with the site...
Tidak buruk. Selama lokasinya baik-baik saja...
I'll go through it.
Akan kuperiksa.
Any bank-related updates for me?
Ada info terkait bank untukku?
Yes, sir. A bank approached us
Ya, Pak. Sebuah bank datang
with an offer to lower the interest rate for a number of loans.
dengan tawaran menurunkan suku bunga untuk sejumlah pinjaman.
They want to discuss it with you over a meal.
Mereka ingin membicarakannya sambil makan.
Do I have to be there?
Aku harus hadir?
I think it'll be good to meet with them in person.
Kurasa sebaiknya kita bertemu langsung.
After that, they also succeeded in detecting a second gravity wave.
Mereka juga berhasil mendeteksi gelombang gravitasi kedua.
It's possible
Bisa jadi,
that third and fourth waves are arriving as we speak,
gelombang ketiga dan keempat muncul detik ini juga,
and there might have been a time and space warp in Seoul.
serta mungkin ada warp waktu dan ruang di Seoul.
We'll learn more about gravity waves on Amazing Science today.
Kita akan mempelajari gelombang gravitasi di Amazing Science hari ini.
Hello.
Halo.
-Any word from the police station? -No, they haven't called.
- Ada kabar dari kantor polisi? - Tidak, belum ada.
Apparently, there might have been a time and space warp in Seoul yesterday.
Sepertinya, mungkin ada warp waktu dan ruang di Seoul kemarin.
Perhaps your diamond ring disappeared when that happened?
Mungkin cincin berlianmu hilang saat itu terjadi?
I bought it at the Dongdaemun Market early this morning.
Aku membelinya di Pasar Dongdaemun pagi ini.
-Wear it for now. -You should've gotten more sleep.
- Pakai saja. - Kau harus lebih banyak tidur.
The doctors' gown is so important for doctors.
Jas dokter penting bagi dokter.
-Doesn't your stomach hurt? -I'm not hungover.
- Perutmu sakit? - Aku tidak pengar.
-Did you have breakfast? -You're nagging again.
- Kau sudah sarapan? - Kau cerewet lagi.
You have no food at home, right?
Kau tak punya makanan di rumah?
I should stop by and make some side dishes.
Aku harus mampir dan membuat makanan.
-Do you have a death wish? -The driver
- Kau mau mati? - Pengemudi
who bumped your car last month, Park Sang-cheol.
yang menyenggol mobilmu bulan lalu, Park Sang-cheol.
He called again.
Dia menelepon lagi.
I took care of everything with the insurance company.
Sudah kuurus dengan asuransi.
I don't even know. He said he'd come here, then he changed his mind.
Aku tak tahu.
I don't know what he wants.
Entah apa maunya.
By the way, when will you go to the bank?
Kapan kau akan ke bank?
Putting it off won't solve the problem.
Menunda sesuatu tak akan menyelesaikannya.
I know that too.
Aku juga tahu itu.
-Any appointments in the morning? -No, obviously.
- Ada janji temu pagi ini? - Jelas tidak.
Your afternoon schedule is empty too, so you can go whenever you want.
Jadwal siangmu juga kosong, jadi kau bisa pergi sesukamu.
The interest too. You always make the payments late.
Bunganya juga. Kau selalu terlambat membayar.
On top of that, you've been managing your credit very poorly.
Dan juga, pengelolaan kreditmu sangat buruk.
You received an extremely low rating in last year's evaluation.
Penilaianmu sangat rendah ketika evaluasi tahun lalu.
Please review it again.
Tolong tinjau lagi.
I've paid all of my taxes. I'm just struggling temporarily.
Aku sudah bayar semua pajakku. Aku hanya sedang sulit sementara ini.
Psychiatric clinics do very well these days.
Klinik kejiwaan sangat laris belakangan ini.
Then...
Kalau begitu...
you can pay part of the amount that you owe
kau bisa membayar setengah jumlah utangmu
and switch to an interest rate that's around seven percent,
dan beralih ke tingkat bunga sekitar tujuh persen,
but I'm not sure if the evaluation team will accept this.
tapi aku tak yakin tim evaluasi akan terima ini.
Seven percent?
Tujuh persen?
How can the interest rate jump from four to seven percent?
Kenapa bunganya meningkat dari 4 ke 7 persen?
Please look into it for me, then.
Tolong tinjau untukku.
WARM WATER
AIR PANAS
Gosh, where did he go?
Astaga, ke mana dia pergi?
BLESSED MENTAL HEALTH NURSE YU SANG-YU
KLINIK JIWA BLESSED PERAWAT YU SANG-YU
2:10 P.M., JUNE 24, 2017
14:10, 24 JUNI 2017
Why is this taking so long?
Kenapa lama sekali?
Excuse me.
Permisi.
Just a moment, please.
Mohon tunggu.
Do I have to wait much longer?
Apa masih lama?
I have to go back to my clinic to attend to patients.
Aku harus kembali ke klinik untuk merawat pasien.
Just a moment, please.
Mohon tunggu sebentar.
Gosh! My goodness!
Astaga.
Sir, did you have a good lunch?
Tuan, bagaimana makan siangnya?
Would you like a cup of pour over coffee made with organic beans?
Mau secangkir kopi yang terbuat dari biji organik?
If you choose to go with our loan services,
Jika menerima pinjaman kami,
-we can offer you one-percent interest. -What? One percent?
- kami bisa menawarkan bunga satu persen. - Apa? Satu persen?
Excuse me.
Permisi.
-I told you to wait. -I can't wait all day.
- Aku menyuruhmu menunggu. - Aku tak bisa menunggu seharian.
You've kept me waiting since this morning.
Kau menyuruhku menunggu sejak pagi ini.
I'm not asking for a new loan. I just want an extension.
Aku tak meminta pinjaman baru. Aku hanya mau perpanjangan.
Is it that hard to check it for me?
Sesulit itukah memeriksanya?
And why are you walking around with my personal information?
Kenapa kau mondar-mandir dengan informasi pribadiku?
Well...
Begini...
Please wait outside.
Tunggulah di luar.
I told you I won't wait any longer.
Aku bilang tak mau menunggu lagi.
And why do I have to pay seven percent when he's getting one percent?
Dan kenapa aku harus membayar 7 persen sementara dia 1 persen?
How can you treat your customers so unfairly?
Kenapa kau tak adil dengan pelangganmu?
-Well, that's-- -I know. I know the reason.
- Itu... - Aku tahu alasannya.
But this is out of line.
Tapi ini keterlaluan.
The difference between one and seven percent is huge!
Perbedaan antara satu hingga tujuh persen besar!
Please help her first.
Tolong urus dia dulu.
You can discuss this with my finance team.
Kau bisa diskusikan ini dengan tim keuanganku.
Sir, wait. You can't just leave like this.
Tuan, tunggu. Jangan pergi begitu saja.
Ma'am, I'd like you to apologize to Mr. Shin.
Nyonya, aku ingin kau minta maaf kepada Pak Shin.
-What did you say? -You just cut in line.
- Apa katamu? - Kau menyela antrean.
He's leaving because he's upset.
Dia pergi karena dia kesal.
That is not true.
Itu tidak benar.
It's the bank's fault for revealing the interest rate to other customers.
Ini salah bank karena mengungkap suku bunga kepada nasabah lain.
-You're the one who should apologize. -Sorry?
Justru kau yang
I'll ask the bank if you could get the loan.
Akan kutanya bank apa kau bisa dapat pinjaman.
Why would you do that for me?
Kenapa kau lakukan itu?
You don't seem to know how to accept kindness.
Sepertinya kebaikan asing bagimu.
Then instead of bothering the bank staff regarding your interest rate,
Daripada mengganggu pegawai bank soal bunga,
you should work harder to earn money on your own.
harusnya kau bekerja lebih keras mencari uang.
-Please visit our clinic. -Okay.
- Silakan kunjungi klinik kami. - Baiklah.
-Right. -Excuse me, sir. Please visit...
- Benar. - Permisi, Pak. Silakan kunjungi...
No, wait. Stop!
Tunggu. Hentikan!
Why would you scrape off bird poop with our business card?
Kenapa kau mengelap kotoran burung dengan kartu nama kami?
Seriously, why would you do that?
Sungguh, kenapa kau melakukannya?
-My goodness. -What's going on?
- Astaga. - Ada apa?
It's nothing, sir.
Bukan apa-apa, Pak.
What happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
Why did you scrape off bird poop with our business card?
Kau mengelap kotoran burung dengan kartu nama kami!
-Why? -Please calm down.
- Kenapa? - Tenanglah.
Please give me a call. I'll take care of this.
Tolong hubungi aku. Aku akan mengurusnya.
A business card is the face of that business.
Kartu nama adalah wajah perusahaan.
You practically wiped bird poop with our clinic's reputation!
Kau seka kotoran burung menggunakan nama klinik kami!
-Enough. Let's go. -Think about it.
Cukup. Ayo.
Why do you think cars have windshield wipers?
Menurutmu kenapa mobil punya wiper?
You're supposed to wipe things off with this.
Seharusnya kau membersihkan dengan ini.
What's the point of having a big car?
Apa gunanya punya mobil besar?
My gosh, I'm so sorry.
Astaga, maafkan aku.
BLESSED MENTAL HEALTH NURSE YU SANG-YU
KLINIK JIWA BLESSED YU SANG-YU
A psychiatric clinic?
Sebuah klinik kejiwaan?
I'll call you when I get an estimate of the repair cost.
Akan kutelepon saat biaya perbaikan keluar.
Hello.
Halo.
My lord.
Tuan.
Where's the map? Did you find it?
Di mana petanya? Kau menemukannya?
I couldn't find it anywhere.
Aku tak menemukannya.
I think we lost it on our way down here.
Kurasa hilang dalam perjalanan ke sini.
On our way here?
Perjalanan ke sini?
-Does that mean we can't find it? -That's right.
- Berarti kita tak bisa menemukannya? - Benar.
By the way, what are you doing out here? I told you to stay home.
Omong-omong, sedang apa di sini? Aku bilang tetaplah di rumah, 'kan?
"Home"?
"Rumah"?
You slept so soundly last night. I thought you were going to stand guard.
Kau tidur pulas semalam. Kau bilang akan berjaga.
I must've fallen asleep because I was tired and hungry.
Aku pasti tertidur karena lelah dan lapar.
-You were hungry? -Yes.
- Kau lapar? - Ya.
I get hungry around mealtimes just like humans do.
Aku merasa lapar saat jam makan seperti manusia.
You probably don't even know what hunger feels like.
Kau mungkin tak tahu bagaimana rasanya.
Do I have to listen to you whining like this?
Apa aku harus mendengarkanmu mengeluh seperti ini?
No.
Tidak.
Are you that hungry?
Kau amat lapar?
Yes, I'm quite hungry.
Ya, lumayan lapar.
I'm sorry.
Maaf.
This is all because I've lost my power.
Ini semua karena aku kehilangan kekuatanku.
I can't even take care of a loyal servant like you.
Aku bahkan tak bisa mengurus pelayan setia sepertimu.
How can I become a good king when I'm this incompetent?
Bagaimana bisa jadi raja yang baik jika aku tak cakap?
What? No! That is not true, my lord!
Apa? Tidak! Itu tak benar, Tuan!
Don't tell me you were actually expecting me to say that.
Jangan bilang kau menungguku mengatakan itu.
Of course not.
Tentu tidak.
By the way, what is that thing?
Omong-omong, benda apa itu?
Well, that's...
Itu jelas...
It's not food.
bukan makanan.
-Let's go to that place. -Sorry? Where?
- Ayo ke sana. - Maaf? Ke mana?
The Divine Gate.
Gerbang Surgawi.
The divine servants have been guarding that place,
Para pelayan surgawi menjaga tempat itu,
so I'm sure we can find out where the descendant is.
aku yakin kita bisa temukan keturunannya.
What? Are you planning to meet the descendant?
Apa? Kau berencana menemui keturunan?
I should give that servant a chance to faithfully serve me...
Aku harus memberi pelayan itu kesempatan untuk melayaniku dengan setia,
as the generous and dutiful god that I am.
mengingat aku adalah dewa yang murah hati
What should we do?
Kita harus bagaimana?
What if that wiper costs a fortune?
Bagaimana jika wiper itu mahal?
Then I might have to move out of my place.
Maka aku harus pindah dari rumahku.
Why did you have to get all riled up like that?
Kenapa kau harus marah seperti itu?
Because he wiped bird poop with our business card.
Karena dia mengelap kotoran burung dengan kartu nama kita.
You love your job too much.
Kau terlalu mencintai pekerjaanmu.
Why did it have to be that guy's car?
Kenapa harus mobil orang itu?
Are you calling Mr. Min?
Kau menelepon Tn. Min?
-Ask him if we can pay less. -Mr. Min, my foot!
Minta supaya jangan terlalu mahal.
Jeez, this realtor never answers my calls.
Astaga, makelar ini tak pernah menjawab teleponku.
Forget it.
Lupakan.
-I have to go to Gangwon Province. -Right now?
Aku mau ke Provinsi Gangwon.
You should probably change your tires first.
Mungkin sebaiknya kau ganti ban dahulu.
You also need to change the brake fluid,
Kau juga perlu mengganti minyak rem,
the navigation device, and...
alat navigasi, dan...
The windshield wiper.
Wiper kaca depan.
Why isn't this working again?
Kenapa ini bermasalah lagi?
Must you make it so obvious that you're a second-hand car?
Haruskah kau perjelas bahwa kau ini mobil bekas?
My gosh.
Astaga.
There we go.
Itu dia.
Did you say you need to go to Jeongbong Village?
Kalian tadi bilang kalian mau ke Desa Jeongbong?
You need to go straight.
Lurus terus.
Just keep going that way.
Teruslah berjalan ke sana.
Then turn left when you feel like you've arrived at the right place.
Belok kiri saat merasa sudah tiba di tempat yang tepat.
Then keep going and turn right when you feel like you've walked enough,
Lalu lurus dan belok kanan saat merasa sudah cukup berjalan.
and you'll eventually arrive at the village. Okay?
Dan kalian akhirnya tiba di desa. Oke?
He just meant that it's not too far from here.
Tempatnya tak terlalu jauh dari sini.
Don't worry. I've been here several times.
Jangan khawatir. Aku pernah ke sana beberapa kali.
No one has called about that land for the past five years.
Tak ada yang mau tanah itu selama lima tahun ini.
That's why I asked you to put up a sign
Karena itu aku memintamu memasang sebuah tanda
and tell people that the land is for sale.
dan memberi tahu orang kalau tanah itu dijual.
Jeez, okay. I heard you.
Astaga, baiklah. Aku mendengarmu.
I came here to ask if I could lower the price to sell it urgently.
Aku kemari untuk bertanya apa aku bisa menurunkan harganya agar cepat terjual?
Even if you lowered the price,
Meski kau menurunkan harganya,
nobody would want to buy such a useless piece of land.
tak ada yang mau membeli tanah yang tak berguna.
Sir.
Pak.
I know it's useless, but you shouldn't say that to the landowner.
Aku tahu itu tak berguna, tapi jangan katakan itu kepada penjual tanah.
So, how much?
Jadi, berapa harganya?
-Is it going to be half the price? -What?
- Turun setengah? - Apa?
This is where we were supposed to land.
Di sinilah kita seharusnya mendarat.
I don't think the gate is visible to humans.
Mestinya gerbangnya tak terlihat oleh manusia.
Why did they build the gate on such an unimpressive piece of land?
Kenapa gerbangnya dibuat di lahan yang tak mengesankan ini?
By the way, that servant won't know a thing. What do we do?
Pelayan itu tak akan tahu apa-apa. Bagaimana ini?
We need to show her the pendant
Kita harus tunjukkan kalungnya
in order for her to realize that she's your servant.
agar dia sadar bahwa dia adalah pelayanmu.
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
I have a plan.
Aku punya rencana.
What's your plan?
Apa itu?
She'll fall for my charm,
Dia akan takluk pada pesonaku,
so she'll naturally want to serve me.
dia tentu ingin melayaniku.
If that doesn't work, I'll have to use my last resort.
Jika itu tak berhasil, aku harus gunakan pilihan terakhirku.
And what might that be?
Apa itu?
What? No, you can't do that.
Apa? Jangan lakukan itu.
-Why not? -You should never do that.
- Kenapa tidak? - Sebaiknya jangan.
Then she'll forget everything,
Lalu dia akan melupakan semuanya,
but that won't be possible if you use that last resort.
tapi itu mustahil jika menggunakan cara terakhir.
That would be too torturous for a human.
Itu terlalu menyiksa bagi manusia.
You've been talking nonsense nonstop since yesterday.
Kau bicara tak masuk akal sejak kemarin.
Most importantly, you've lost your power. How will that even work?
Apalagi, kekuatanmu hilang.
What does that have to do with my power? Am I not a god without my power?
Apa hubungannya dengan kekuatanku? Apa aku bukan dewa tanpa kekuatanku?
Why don't you take my place, then?
Kenapa kau tak menggantikanku?
My gosh, how could you say such a thing? No way, my lord.
Astaga, kenapa kau berkata begitu? Tidak, Tuan.
Excuse me.
Permisi.
May I ask what brings you here?
Boleh aku bertanya kalian sedang apa?
I own this land.
Aku pemilik tanah ini.
It was you.
Ternyata kau.
Let go of her. Don't do this.
Lepaskan dia. Jangan begitu.
I'm the God of Water,
Aku Dewa Air,
the next king of the Land of Water, and the next emperor of the gods,
calon Raja Negeri Air, dan calon kaisar para dewa,
Habaek.
Habaek.
What is he doing here?
Sedang apa dia di sini?
-Are you the owner of this land? -Yes, I am.
- Kau pemilik tanah ini? - Ya.
-Are you here to buy this land? -Why would I buy my own land?
- Kau mau beli tanah ini? - Membeli tanahku sendiri?
What?
Apa?
I've looked all over for you, my faithful servant.
Aku mencarimu ke mana-mana, pelayanku yang setia.
I'm very glad to finally meet you.
Aku senang akhirnya berjumpa denganmu.
You should be grateful...
Kau seharusnya bersyukur
that I'm glad to meet you.
aku gembira bertemu denganmu.
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
How dare you.
Lancang sekali.
You know you're cut out to be a psychiatrist, right?
Kau tahu kau cocok jadi psikiater, bukan?
People who need you come to you day and night.
Orang yang membutuhkanmu datang siang dan malam.
I need to go see Yeom-mi.
Aku harus menemui Yeom-mi.
I think it's time.
Kurasa sudah saatnya.
Please give me a heads-up before you do anything.
Tolong beri tahu aku sebelum kau melakukan apa pun.
Hey, Yeom-mi. Are you free tonight?
Seon-mi, kau tak sibuk malam ini?
No, you must make time for me. We need to meet.
Tidak, kau harus meluangkan waktu untukku. Kita harus bertemu.
I'm in Gangwon Province right now. Oh, gosh!
Aku di Provinsi Gangwon sekarang. Astaga!
Why? What's wrong?
Kenapa? Ada apa?
Hey, I'll call you later.
Akan kutelepon nanti.
Are you okay? Let me see.
Kau baik-baik saja? Biar kulihat.
No, I'm fine.
Tidak, aku baik-baik saja.
-He is not fine. -Right, I don't think I'm fine.
- Dia tak baik-baik saja. - Benar.
I'm not fine.
Aku terluka.
You've entered the route to your destination.
Rute tujuan telah dimasukkan.
I'll drop you off at a hospital nearby.
Aku akan mengantarmu ke rumah sakit terdekat.
Let's call the insurance company there.
Kita hubungi asuransi di sana.
-No. We're coming with you. -Turn left.
- Tidak. Kami ikut denganmu. - Belok kiri.
Excuse me.
Tunggu.
He said he's not fine. He can't go all the way to Seoul.
Dia bilang dia terluka. Dia tak bisa pergi jauh ke Seoul.
And can't you talk politely?
Dan bicaralah dengan sopan.
I don't know what you mean. Just try to have an awakening soon.
Aku tak paham maksudmu. Cepatlah sadar,
Then you'll understand the situation.
maka kau akan memahami semuanya.
Understanding the situation will make things so much easier.
Dengan begitu, segalanya jadi mudah.
What is he saying?
Apa maksudnya?
Look. Is there a specific clinic that you normally go to?
Dengar, apa ada klinik khusus yang biasa kau datangi?
If not, you can come to my...
Jika tak ada, kau bisa datang ke...
What am I saying?
Kenapa aku berkata begitu?
Excuse me.
Maaf.
I'm a doctor. Your friend here is--
Aku seorang dokter. Temanmu ini…
He's not my friend. He's my servant.
Dia bukan temanku. Dia pelayanku.
Your servant...
Pelayanmu…
I mean, that guy sitting next to you
Maksudku, pria yang duduk di sebelahmu
seems fine to me.
tampaknya baik-baik saja.
I'm taking you with me because I don't want to get sued,
Aku membawamu karena aku tak mau digugat,
-so let's just settle. -I don't understand what you're saying.
- mari kita selesaikan. - Aku tak paham ucapanmu.
I don't think I came this way.
Kurasa aku tadi tak lewat sini.
Turn right.
Belok kanan.
There's no road that turns right.
Tak ada belokan ke kanan.
Go straight ahead until further instruction.
Lurus terus sampai instruksi berikutnya.
I don't think I'm going in the right direction.
Kurasa arahnya salah.
Turn right.
Belok kanan.
Turn left.
Belok kiri.
Go straight ahead until further instruction.
Lurus terus sampai instruksi berikutnya.
Make a U-turn.
Putar balik.
Turn left.
Belok kiri.
-This is nuts. -Beware of the bend on your left.
- Ini gila. - Hati-hati tikungan di sebelah kiri.
Go straight.
Lurus terus.
-There's no road here! -Then make a P-turn.
- Tidak ada jalan! - Kalau begitu, putar balik.
-Where are you telling me to go? -This is an unpaved road.
- Ke mana? - Ini jalan tak beraspal.
Go straight ahead. Please drive safely.
Lurus terus. Hati-hati dalam berkendara.
-Are you tired? -Yes.
- Kau lelah? - Ya.
What can I do for you?
Ada yang bisa kubantu?
Nothing.
Tak ada.
Do you want me to drive?
Kau mau aku yang menyetir?
Do you have a driver's license?
Kau punya SIM?
What's that?
Apa itu?
Never mind.
Lupakan saja.
Doctors should never let their patients drive.
Dokter seharusnya tak membiarkan pasiennya mengemudi.
Turn right.
Belok kanan.
SERVICE UNAVAILABLE
TIDAK ADA SINYAL
No!
Tidak!
What's going on?
Ada apa?
The car stopped because it ran out of gas.
Mobilnya berhenti karena kehabisan bensin.
Then get her some gas.
Beri dia bensin.
How?
Bagaimana caranya?
Can I use your phone?
Boleh aku pinjam ponselmu?
Your cell phone.
Ponselmu.
Don't you have one?
Kau tak punya?
Fine. Let's walk, then.
Baiklah. Kita jalan saja.
I'm sure we'll run into someone.
Kita akan bertemu seseorang.
Let's borrow a cell phone and call my insurance company,
Kita pinjam ponsel dan hubungi perusahaan asuransiku,
or we can try to go buy gas ourselves.
atau kita coba beli bensin.
I don't understand what you're saying,
Aku tak paham maksudmu,
but you should get some rest.
kau harus istirahat.
-What? -You said you're tired.
- Apa? - Kau bilang kau lelah.
Stay here and get some rest. Namsuri will go by himself.
Istirahatlah di sini. Namsuri akan pergi sendiri.
But he's hurt.
Tapi dia terluka.
Yes, I'm in pain.
Ya, aku kesakitan.
-He's not hurt. -I think I'm okay now.
- Dia tidak terluka. - Benar.
-I feel fine. -Go on.
- Aku merasa sehat. - Pergilah.
No, it's okay. I'll go. It won't take long.
Tidak apa-apa. Aku akan pergi. Tak akan lama.
My gosh, what are you doing?
Astaga, apa yang kau lakukan?
I don't even know where I am now.
Aku bahkan tak tahu di mana aku sekarang.
Wait.
Tunggu.
Yes?
Ya?
My license plate number
Ini nomor pelat mobilku
and the insurance company's number are written here.
dan nomor perusahaan asuransi.
And here's some money for gas. Oh, just a second.
Dan ini uang untuk besin. Tunggu sebentar.
I almost forgot to give you this.
Aku hampir lupa memberimu ini.
All right.
Baiklah.
Why is everything...
Kenapa segalanya
so difficult today?
sangat rumit hari ini?
Excuse me.
Permisi.
You can wait inside the car.
Tunggulah di mobil.
I'm okay, so you go ahead and rest up in the car.
Aku tak apa-apa, jadi kau istirahat saja di mobil.
My name is Habaek, not "Excuse me."
Namaku Habaek, bukan "Maaf."
I'm the God of Water, the next king of the Land of Water,
Aku Dewa Air, calon Raja Negeri Air,
and the next emperor of the gods.
dan calon raja para dewa.
And...
Dan...
I am your master.
aku adalah tuanmu.
Ha...
Namaku...
baek.
Habaek.
Gosh, I keep forgetting that he's mentally ill.
Astaga, aku terus lupa kalau dia sakit jiwa.
Excuse...
Ma...
I mean, Mr. Habaek.
Tn. Habaek.
Why do you think that you're the God of Water?
Kenapa kau pikir kau adalah Dewa Air?
What kind of question is that?
Pertanyaan macam apa itu?
Then let me ask you this. Why do you think you're human?
Aku akan balik bertanya. Kenapa kau berpikir kau manusia?
Fine.
Baiklah.
Then,
Kalau begitu,
what exactly is the God of Water?
apa itu Dewa Air?
What are you trying to do right now?
Apa maksudmu?
Are you seeking to gain knowledge?
Kau ingin mencari pengetahuan?
It seems like you wish to talk about the essence of the world.
Sepertinya kau ingin membicarakan esensi dari dunia.
Listen to me carefully.
Dengarkan baik-baik.
The God of Water, the God of the Sky, and the God of Earth.
Dewa Air, Dewa Langit, dan Dewa Tanah,
We are equal to nature itself.
semua setara dengan alam itu sendiri.
Thus,
Jadi,
I am nature.
aku adalah alam.
-Are you talking about the TV show? -I said, I am nature.
- Maksudmu acara TV? - Kubilang, aku adalah alam.
-The show, I Am a Natural Person? -No, I am nature. More importantly,
Acara Aku Manusia Alami?
I am the most essential part of nature.
aku bagian paling penting dari alam.
What?
Apa?
I mean, he looks completely normal.
Dia terlihat normal.
Stop peeping at me.
Berhenti mengintipku.
I can see it even with my eyes closed.
Aku bisa melihat bahkan saat mataku tertutup.
I'm so used to others looking at me like that.
Tatapan orang lain seperti itu biasa bagiku.
Sure,
Tentu,
I bet.
aku yakin itu.
You have...
Kau punya
a family, right?
keluarga, 'kan?
I can say that I do, but then I can also say that I don't.
Ya sekaligus tidak.
The notion of family is different in the divine realm.
Gagasan keluarga berbeda di kayangan.
Then who's that guy--
Lalu siapa pria itu...
I told you that he's my servant. Like you.
Sudah kubilang dia pelayanku. Seperti dirimu.
He's my servant from the divine realm,
Dia pelayanku dari kayangan dan
-Hey, servant. -Yes?
- Hei, pelayan. - Ya.
-Hey. -Call me Lord Habaek!
- Hei. - Panggil aku Tuan Habaek!
Is money really what you need...
Apa hal yang paling kau butuhkan
the most?
adalah uang?
Why do you ask?
Kenapa kau bertanya?
Why do humans need money so much?
Kenapa manusia butuh uang banyak?
It's because money can make you happy.
Itu karena uang bisa membuat orang bahagia.
You too?
Termasuk kau?
Yes. Why?
Ya.
I think..
Kurasa...
I can help you with it.
aku bisa membantumu soal itu.
But not right now.
Tapi tak sekarang.
I'm in a bit of a situation now.
Aku sedang dalam masalah.
Why do I keep on letting him fool me?
Kenapa aku terus membiarkan dia menipuku?
Hey, servant.
Pelayanku.
You said money is what you need the most,
Kau bilang uang adalah hal yang paling kau butuhkan,
but money will give you happiness.
dan uang akan memberimu kebahagiaan.
Therefore, happiness must be what you really need the most.
Jadi, kebahagiaan adalah hal yang paling kau butuhkan.
You don't even know anything about me.
Kau bahkan tak tahu apa-apa tentangku.
I have no interest whatsoever in a mere woman's happiness,
Aku tak tertarik pada kebahagiaan wanita,
so I will repay you with money.
aku akan membalasmu dengan uang.
We should look for it together.
Kita harus mencari bersama.
-Are we going the right way? -I'm not sure.
- Arahnya benar? - Aku tak yakin.
I think we're lost.
Kita tersesat.
You're calmer than I expected you to be.
Kau lebih tenang dari dugaanku.
I have to stay calm, of course.
Aku harus tetap tenang.
I'm your guardian at the moment.
Aku menjagamu saat ini.
"Guardian"?
"Menjaga"?
Yes.
Ya.
You may find it hard to believe, but I have a medical license.
Mungkin sulit dipercaya, tapi aku punya izin praktik.
I hope your underling or colleague, whoever he is, went the right way.
Kuharap bawahan atau rekanmu, siapa pun dia, pergi ke arah yang benar.
We shouldn't keep going.
Kita tak bisa terus jalan.
We should go back.
Kita harus kembali.
-I've been wanting to say that. -Hey, I'll lead the way.
- Aku ingin mengatakan itu. - Hei, aku yang di depan.
Hey, servant.
Pelayanku.
This is your last warning.
Ini peringatan terakhirmu.
Listen carefully.
Dengar baik-baik.
I'm not "Hey." You have to call me Lord Habaek.
Aku bukan "Hei." Kau harus memanggilku Tuan Habaek.
The God of Water, the next king of the Land of Water,
Dewa Air, calon Raja Negeri Air,
and the next emperor of the divine world,
calon kaisar kayangan,
Habaek.
Habaek.
Now, it's your turn to listen up.
Giliranmu untuk mendengar.
My name is Yun So-a, not "Servant."
Namaku Yun So-a, bukan "Pelayan."
Since I'm acting as your guardian now,
Karena kini aku menjadi penjagamu,
it'd be nice if you could call me Dr. Yun.
alangkah baiknya jika kau memanggilku Dokter Yun.
If you don't want to do that, please at least call me Ms. Yun.
Jika tak mau, tolong panggil aku Nn. Yun.
Are we clear?
Jelas?
How insolent.
Lancang sekali.
-What is it? -Run!
- Ada apa? - Lari!
Wait, let's get in the car. Gosh!
Masuk ke mobil. Astaga!
The trunk!
Bagasi!
Why is it all quiet now?
Kenapa sekarang hening?
I think it's gone.
Kurasa sudah aman.
-Are you okay? -I'm very uncomfortable right now.
- Kau tak apa? - Aku merasa tidak nyaman.
Pardon?
Apa?
Don't move. You're making it worse.
Jangan bergerak. Makin parah.
Okay.
Baik.
I think it's gone. Let's open it and see.
Kurasa sudah aman. Ayo kita buka.
What is that?
Apa itu?
Gosh, it smiled! It actually smiled.
Astaga, babinya tersenyum! Benar-benar tersenyum.
What a crazy boar!
Babi hutan gila!
Lord Habaek.
Tuan Habaek.
Can you walk?
Kau bisa jalan?
Let's rest up for a few minutes.
Mari istirahat sebentar.
What happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
I got lost in the woods and met a hunter.
Aku tersesat di hutan dan bertemu pemburu.
I'm so glad he came with me.
Untung dia ikut bersamaku.
Where is he?
Di mana dia?
He followed the boar.
Mengejar babi hutan itu.
Did you get hurt?
Kau terluka?
Well, I thought you couldn't drive.
Kukira kau tak bisa menyetir.
I couldn't.
Aku tak bisa.
Then what's happening now?
Lalu sekarang kau sedang apa?
I'm a good driver now.
Sekarang bisa.
I've never done this before, but it's fun.
Aku belum pernah melakukan ini, tapi ini menyenangkan.
What?
Apa?
Does that mean you don't have a driver's license?
Apa ini artinya kau tak punya SIM?
-What is a driver's license? -Hey!
- Apa itu SIM? - Hei!
Pull over right now. I'll drive.
Menepilah. Aku yang menyetir.
Just get some rest!
Istirahatlah!
This is a huge honor for you, so don't reject my kind gesture.
Ini kehormatan besar bagimu, jadi jangan menolak kebaikanku.
I am just doing what I should do as the generous and dutiful god that I am.
Aku melakukan kewajibanku sebagai dewa yang murah hati dan bertanggung jawab.
Hey!
Hei!
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
Lord Habaek possesses some incredible abilities
Tuan Habaek memiliki kekuatan luar biasa
that humans can't even imagine.
yang tak terbayangkan manusia.
Abilities, my foot. Pull over right now!
Kepalamu! Menepi sekarang!
I said, pull over!
Menepi!
Is this where you live?
Kau tinggal di sini?
-Did you lie to us? -What are you talking about? I lied?
Kau berbohong?
Anyway,
Omong-omong,
thank you for everything today.
terima kasih atas segalanya.
It happened a long time ago.
Kejadiannya sudah sangat lama.
An unknown ancestor of yours made a promise with the gods.
Seorang leluhurmu yang tak dikenal membuat janji dengan para dewa.
He made a pledge that his family would serve the gods for generations.
Dia bersumpah bahwa keluarga dan keturunanya akan melayani para dewa.
You didn't make that promise, but that's beside the point.
Bukan kau yang bersumpah, tapi itu bukan intinya.
You're a descendant of the man who made that promise.
Kau keturunan pria yang bersumpah itu.
Therefore, you must serve me if I want you to.
Jadi, kau harus melayaniku jika kuminta.
Take me to your house.
Bawa aku ke rumahmu.
No. You can go to the hospital instead.
Tidak. Kau lebih baik pergi
If you refuse, you will suffer.
Jika kau menolak, kau akan menderita.
It doesn't matter because I'm already having a hard enough time.
Tak masalah karena hidupku penuh penderitaan.
You're right.
Kau benar.
Happiness may be what I truly want
Kebahagiaan mungkin hal yang amat kuinginkan
because I'm really exhausted.
karena aku sangat lelah.
So, do me a favor...
Maka tolonglah
and leave me alone.
jangan ganggu aku.
Please.
Kumohon.
I can't believe she still hasn't realized her fate
Aku tak percaya dia belum menyadari takdirnya
after everything I've taught her.
setelah semua yang aku katakan kepadanya.
How foolish.
Bodoh sekali.
I guess I have no choice.
Tak ada pilihan lain.
Namsuri.
Namsuri.
Because of what you said,
Karena ucapanmu, aku tidak mau menggunakan pilihan terakhirku
But now, I have no choice.
Tapi tak ada jalan lain.
But, my lord,
Tapi Tuan, kekuatanmu bisa...
I shall grace you with my blessing,
Aku akan memberimu rahmat,
so wake up already.
jadi bangunlah.
Don't you feel like something in your heart...
Kau tak merasakan sesuatu di hatimu…
Why did I close my eyes?
Kenapa aku menutup mataku?
Doesn't it feel like something in your heart's smacking your head?
Apa rasanya seperti isi hatimu memukuli kepalamu?
-Absolutely not! -You slow-witted woman! I'm right here!
Tidak!
Gosh, what a psycho!
Astaga, dasar sinting.
-It must be fate. -You now belong to the deity.
- Ini pasti takdir. - Sekarang kau milik dewa.
-You're wrong. -I'm so sick of this nonsense about gods.
- Kau salah. - Aku muak dengan omong kosong dewa ini.
Accept your fate, or you must go through everything.
Terimalah takdirmu, atau hidupmu akan sulit.
What do you mean by "everything"?
Bukan ini kesulitan yang akan kuhadapi.
No!
Tidak!
-She's falling! -Get her!
- Dia jatuh. - Tangkap dia!
Please save me.
Tolong selamatkan aku.
Will we leave right away?
Kita segera pergi?
Yes, I left while he was painting me.
Ya, aku pergi saat dia melukisku.
Exactly.
Tepat.
You could've told him to come back later on.
Kau bisa suruh dia kembali nanti.
Why are you punishing him?
Kenapa menghukumnya?
EPILOGUE
EPILOG
When did I punish him?
Kapan aku menghukumnya?
When is Lord Habaek coming back?
Kapan Tuan Habaek kembali?
I should've drawn his eyes when I had the chance to.
Aku seharusnya melukis matanya selagi sempat.